It's the busiest time in the countryside calendar, as farmers gather in the fruits of their labour.
But making hay, and everything else, while the sun shines isn't proving that easy this year.
Welcome to Countryfile, from the harvest fields of Warwickshire.
For arable farmers right across the nation, this is crunch time.
A race against the clock - and the weather - to bring in the harvest.
A rainy August has put things badly behind, so now, there's an awful lot at stake.
A good harvest means a good year for farmers, a bad one can spell disaster.
So we've come to Warwickshire in the country's agricultural heartland to check on how things are going.
Harvest is also the most dangerous time for farmers, and we'll be looking into the grim statistic that agriculture has the worst health and safety record in the United Kingdom.
And we'll be meeting a farmer with a passion for filming wildlife.
Also on today's Countryfile - should the UK become more self-sufficient in food production?
We're not talking Fortress Britain, but how we produce our food is so dependent on other countries' land.
Keeping tabs on these enigmatic visitors to Britain's beaches.
The jellyfish are very large animals, up to 30kg, they're the size of dustbins!
They're very robust, they're not flimsy at all.
And Julia takes a trip back in time when she visits the world's oldest model village.
Mind the sheep!
Oh, yeah, mustn't tread on the sheep!
Farmers have many problems to contend with.
Right now, the big worry is the escalating cost of animal feed and fertilizer.
But the constant concern, year after year, and heightened at harvest time, is the weather.
David Jones is a big time farmer.
He runs a 2,500 acre arable farm here in Warwickshire and another in Bedfordshire.
One of the wettest Augusts on record has put back the harvest by at least two weeks.
Before we met him, he'd brought in only 250 acres of wheat.
So, how are things going, David?
Considering the weather, things are going OK.
The wind's blowing at the moment, the crop's dry, so we're able to cut.
The combine's out, doing its job!
In fact, it looks in pretty good condition to me!
Yeah, as you can see, the crop's still stood up, so that's a huge advantage to us.
And I suppose if you did have dampness and the crop was flattened and you couldn't get it in on time, you'd lose a lot of value, wouldn't you?
Yeah.
This is a milling variety, so we want the quality in there to sell at a premium price.
If it was no good for milling, it would go for animal feed?
We've spent all year growing this for the quality, and it comes down to the last few weeks of the year that determine that.
If we can have another good 10, 12 days, we'll be breaking the back of it.
Last year, with the world shortage of wheat, he got good prices.
But this year, with no shortage expected, plus the downturn in the global economy, it's not looking as good for farmers like David, who've ploughed big money into the latest farm technology.
It's a high-investment business these days.
That combine must cost you a lot of money.
Yeah, they're expensive machines.
We need to get the output out of them to justify them.
And the fuel for them, these days!
Yeah, the fuel this year has doubled in price for us to buy.
That particular machine is costing around £600 a day in fuel.
The biggest problem is the volatility of the market.
Growing prices have dipped, but our overall costs dramatically rose.
Generally, things have rose 35 per cent in the last 12 months.
Fuel has doubled, fertilizers have rose 150 per cent, seeds have all gone up...
So for you over the next few months, it's going to be a gamble as to how much you plant and what you plant.
It's a very big gamble.
Farmers are selling grain now to fund fertilizer for next year.
We've got fertilizer in the store that won't be used till next March/April, that's all got to be paid for.
So it's tricky times.
So far, less than half the national wheat crop has been harvested.
That's way behind schedule.
And it'll all have to be dried, pushing up the costs.
Farms of all sizes are affected.
George Browning has an 80 acre organic farm in Warwickshire.
As well as his wheat, he's worried about the hay that will feed his herd of 18 Shetland cattle this winter.
Despite all the rain, George, you've managed to mow your hay.
Well, I've mown it yesterday, but it's very late in the year and at this of the year, I need four, five, six days before it's going to be ready to do anything with.
I've now burned my boats, I've got to have fine weather, otherwise it'll rot and it'll be no good to me then.
And if it's wet now, how damp is it?
It's very wet, that's because it's just been mown.
It would normally be wet, even when it's just been mown in midsummer.
But what you then need is the weather to do the job for you, so wind and sun will dry that out.
You can see bits of it - it's started, the grass itself, on the top, that's much drier.
If it was just all like that, that's getting to the stage where you could do something with that.
You need this organic hay for your organic cattle, don't you?
Absolutely, because they need to have something to eat in the winter, when they're inside and haven't got any grass to eat in the field.
So what's going to happen if the worst occurs and it just rains and rains?
What are the consequences?
If we can't get the hay in and we're all organic, it's really serious, because trying to get organic hay from somewhere else, even if it's available, will be very difficult and expensive.
If we can't feed organic hay and have to buy non-organic hay, the cattle will maybe lose their organic status.
So I'm really praying that we get some good, fine, sunny weather for at least a week - sunshine and wind, that's what we want.
Let's pray for good weather!
Yup.
Piles of grain are now mounting up right across the nation as the harvest comes in.
But here in the UK, we produce only 60 per cent of all the food that we eat.
Everything else is imported.
With global pressure such as rising oil prices and climate change and the growth in bio-fuels, they all affect food prices and food supplies.
It seems that the world is becoming a less predictable place.
So here in the UK, should we become more self-sufficient to ensure our food supply for the future?
Here's Miriam.
As a country, we used to produce all of the food we ate.
But that was back in the middle of the 19th century.
Things have changed, though.
We're now just 60 per cent self-sufficient in all foods, although we do grow all our own cereals.
But DEFRA have decided to get involved.
How much food we produce, how much we import and where from is part of its current discussion paper into ensuring the UK's food security.
We import £20 billion of food every year, mostly products our climate can't sustain.
But in a world faced with climate change and rising oil prices, is it wise not to have total control of our food supply?
So, should we become more self-sufficient?
Would it be practical?
What would be the knock-on effects?
And would it secure future food supplies?
One of the biggest organic farming bodies, the Soil Association, wants us to be more independent, especially in the foods we can grow here.
So how self-sufficient is the Soil Association proposing we be?
We don't know for certain, but we think up to 75 per cent, maybe a bit more.
We're not talking 100 per cent, Fortress Britain.
I still want to drink tea, I like bananas, I like citrus fruit.
And trade is part of our food security.
But how we produce our food is so dependent on other countries' land and on oil from overseas as well.
At the moment, things are OK.
Here we are in this lovely orchard, good English apples growing, the sun's out, maybe we feel all right.
These are one of our biggest imports though, aren't they?
Apples?
Ironically, because Britain has a marvellous climate and a variety of apples, we should be eating fresh apples right through the season.
But we import an awful lot of apples.
We've got 2,500 varieties here - how many do you see in the supermarkets?
Two or three.
That's because of consumer choice - people have decide they want their French Golden Delicious instead.
And fundamentally, this all comes down to the consumer.
Well, it does, but it also comes down to the way food is presented, and the presence of oil, which drives the whole food system, whether it's the production or the distribution or the packing, has almost enabled supermarkets to say, "There are no seasons, "there is just one permanent global summer time, "we'll bring food in from all around the world."
We're not talking about a diet of mangel-wurzels and only rhubarb in the winter, of course there are going to be foods imported still.
But how are we going to feed this country when the oil, if not runs out, is a hell of a lot more expensive and a lot harder to get hold of?
Others, though, are satisfied with the status quo.
Lord Haskins is the former chairman of Northern Foods and has advised the government on rural affairs.
You're a British farmer yourself.
Wouldn't you like to see British farmers and Britain be a self-sufficient nation?
No.
I'm a British farmer, but I'm also a British citizen and I'm also a European citizen.
And I believe that the world is going to grow through free trade, through people selling and buying from each other.
I want this country to be growing as much food as it can, but also buying in food from other people.
In exchange for that, we should be selling other of our skills, financial services, resources, to other people.
The food security issue is about German submarines in the war and supplies being interrupted in two world wars.
That's isn't going to happen again, it's not possible.
We have plenty of food to go around, plenty of money to buy what we need.
What about the threat of rising oil prices?
Surely that could impact on the cost of food we might import.
Obviously, if it costs more to import food, that should give British farmers a competitive advantage.
But there's a limit to the amount of food we can grow in this country.
If we let rip, there would be huge environmental consequences.
It was the repeal of the corn laws in the 19th century which opened up our borders to trade.
By the time of WWII, we were only producing a third of what we needed to sustain the population.
War made us realise how vulnerable a break in food supplies would make us.
So the nation dug for victory.
After WWII, the government encouraged farmers to intensify food production.
They paid them subsidies to grub up apple orchards in order to plant cereal crops like wheat and barley.
It wasn't until the '70s and '80s that we became most self-sufficient, around 70 per cent.
But that led to the infamous wine lakes and butter mountains.
Today, two thirds of our imports come from the European Union.
No single country accounts for more than 13 per cent of what we import.
That way, DEFRA says, we spread the risk and limit any impact of a break in food supplies.
Opinions on our approach to self-sufficiency may be divided, but just how practical is it?
A joint research programme by some of our universities has looked at how we use our land and how any changes would affect our economy, landscape, and even our diet.
If we ate more seasonally, that would help.
But also, if we ate a more plant-based diet, then that would be a more efficient way of producing food.
I think a lot of people are suggesting that.
That we become vegetarians?
Well, yes, in that otherwise you've got to grow something for the animal to eat, and then you eat the animal, so if you cut out the middle animal, then we can go straight to eating the plant-based products.
So, if we became more self-sufficient, we might have to accept a change in diet.
But will it change our countryside?
There's already tremendous pressure on it for more housing, and to grow bio-fuels.
Set-aside land is being brought back into production.
So do we have enough space to grow more food?
And will it alter the landscape?
How big is this field, Adam?
It's a 25 acre field.
How much wheat does it produce?
Hopefully, it doesn't make too much - about 75 tonnes of wheat.
That's about an average sort of crop, really.
If you wanted to intensify the yield in this field, what would you have to do?
We'd have to get more plant food, we'd have to re-drain it, because the drains here were put in 100 years ago and they're rather worn out.
We'd have to use more pesticides to stop the spread of disease and insects in the crop.
And possibly use more modern varieties of wheat as well.
Is that a bad thing?
It doesn't suit our farming system here.
We're all in the credit crunch and facing how much money we spend, and I'm growing more wheat, but will I make any more money out of it?
It's the law of diminishing returns - I spend more on it, but I could spend £100 and gain £80 worth of crop, so is it really worth it for me, as a farmer?
How would the field look if you intensified production?
It depends how far I went.
I could take out the oak trees, which are hundreds of years old.
I wouldn't want to see that and I'm sure the consumer wouldn't either, but we could plough closer to the trees, we might damage the roots, we could take out the field margins we've got round the field, which is about three per cent of the field, and grow crops close to the hedge.
We could take the footpath out of the field, it's taking out a 500 metre strip of crop production.
It's not realistic, perhaps, to talk about 100 per cent self-sufficiency, but if we significantly increase the amount of food we produce, it could have an impact on our countryside, on our economy and on our diets.
We could grow more British food, it is possible, if we, as consumers, demand it and are prepared to face the consequences.
They say that necessity is the mother of invention.
That's certainly true of Countryfile viewer Pete Smith, who's on a mission to breathe new life into old things.
Hello there.
My name's Pete Smith.
I'm an inventor.
I'd like you to see just a few of my inventions.
This little alarm can be adapted to actually go on a push-bike, so if it's stolen, you'll soon know about it and so will the thief.
You have a piece of cat gut on a staple, held to a firm surface, A little key goes in the back of the alarm, which is fixed under the saddle, and as I take the bike away...
ALARM BLARES ..the alarm is activated, so any thief would just dump the bike, walk away and disown himself from it.
Here's another one for you.
This is a £3 smoke alarm to try and keep ownership of your car.
A piece of plastic tube from an overflow pipe from a toilet, a magnet, which you can get anywhere, a pipe click and a neck of a bottle.
Basically, how it works is this area here is shoved up the exhaust pipe, the gases go down to the area of the smoke alarm, and as somebody drives your car away, this alarm will go off, there's no way of stopping it, and hopefully, you'll see a pair of car doors open down the road and the would-be thieves will have legged it.
On the serious side of my inventing, I've worked in the environment for the last 10 years, recycling material that really can't be recycled.
For instance, this is a waste bin, obviously, from looking at it, made out of aeroplane wheels.
I've also done a lobster pot over here.
How it worked was we had a pot neck here, the rubber was very good because it was twice as strong in the water as out, being so cold, the lobster would come up here, fall through the neck, and just awaiting the fishermen bringing it in, really.
It's not too hard to see that taking this design, I took it over for a rubber gabion, which is our next one we see.
A rubber gabion is to be filled with stone and holding back banks.
This is a miniature version of this - this is called a bankshore.
Every part of this has been recycled.
You can actually roll it over and use it as a wheel and one person can actually roll it into position a long distance away.
And now let me show you how the bankshore is merged into the environment and what a difference it can make.
Well, here we are on the West Looe river, near Looe, and this is a fantastic repair work that my bankshore has done in actually taking the side of the riverbank that has fallen down, causing the bridge problems.
It's repaired the river, its lay-by to the river is losing its volume, and is going out at a slower speed, causing less trouble further down and less erosion.
People say I talk a lot.
But out here, fishing, this is where the talk stops and the thinking starts.
To be an inventor, you need, really, something inside you that can see the obvious where other people haven't seen it before.
It's really more of a devotion, rather than a job.
Excuse me, I feel another invention coming on!
Thanks very much for the day.
There's not a soul around on this farm right now, because everyone is out in the fields, gathering in the harvest.
It's the busiest time of year on arable farms, and also the most dangerous.
In the past 10 years, 399 people have lost their lives on British farms.
And of those, 134 - that's a third of the total - died at harvest time.
The emergency services called to farms, sadly, a more frequent sight these days, as agriculture becomes the nation's most hazardous industry.
By far and away the biggest killer is moving vehicles - tractors, trailers, combines - moving around.
Working at height - people falling from ladders, fragile roofs.
And then other things like livestock, which are inherently unpredictable.
At this time of year in particular, we're looking at a lot of machinery working and people getting their hands, arms, legs caught in bits of moving machinery.
It can happen so easily.
Just one careless moment is all it takes.
Someone who knows that full well is the vice-president of the National Farmers Union Paul Temple.
What happened to you, Paul?
I was an enthusiastic 16-year-old in a rush to get a field baled up.
There was a blockage, I jumped off the machine and tried to clear the blockage with my foot.
The equipment caught hold of me and dragged me into the machine.
What were your injuries?
I was lucky that I managed to get out but it badly damaged my right leg.
There were several people injured that year, and a fatality.
You're vice-president of a union in an industry which has the worst fatality rate of any industry in Britain, what are you going to do about that?
It's a challenging record and we'd like to better it.
There's several areas, whether it's training, awarenesss and investment, and encouraging the government to allow better investment in working conditions and training is a key priority for us.
Most of the accidents on farms at this time of year are due to people rushing to get the harvest in.
To a certain extent, there is this issue of difficult conditions and trying to make the most of the small windows of operating that we've actually got.
And it can lead to people either missing something or, as I've done, trying to take a short cut.
Invariably, short cuts don't work.
With health and safety now such an issue in agriculture, potential dangers need highlighting.
Let's look round this typical farm.
Bales of straw and hay building up here.
What about these?
These, on the face of it, are actually stacked quite well.
The things we'd have to watch for would be unstable ones.
If one of those fell on you...
You're talking of something that weighs in excess of half a tonne.
500 kilos falling from 3 or 4 metres high won't have much mercy on a human body.
Every farm has a tractor, some of them very big like this one, potentially dangerous.
Yeah.
It's 7 or 8 tonnes at least in weight so a lot of momentum, a lot of energy, hundreds of horsepower.
Make sure all the guards are in place, particularly things like this power takeoff shaft...
The drive shaft.
What would happen if that wasn't properly guarded?
Within this guard, the shaft is revolving at 540 revs per minute.
At that speed, if you got caught in it, it would potentially wrap 6ft of clothing per second.
You'd have very little chance of escaping.
It could take your arm off.
It could potentially kill you.
Because most farms have small workforces and many are family businesses, accidents can be devastating in every way.
As an inspector, I've investigated some horrific injuries and accidents.
They're deeply personal.
These are small businesses, so they have a profound effect on both the business and on the families of those who were killed or injured.
And most of these accidents can be prevented.
We all know that Ben likes to take on difficult tasks.
He's rowed the Atlantic and right now, he's preparing to walk to the South Pole.
But a very different kind of challenge faced him when he tried his hand at a traditional sport.
There was only one thing on his mind - winning.
Some people think there's a little bit too much sport on TV.
If you're one of those people... don't look away just yet... because this is a very different kind of sport altogether.
I'm in one of the greatest sporting arenas in the world for the game of quoits.
It's been played here in Beck Hole on the North York moors, since the 19th century, but the origins of the sport go back to ancient Greece.
This game was filmed in 1983.
Today, its popularity may be limited mainly to the Northeast of England and parts of Scotland but it's played with real passion.
To show me the basics, I get my first coaching session with the 1990 world champion Colin Gray.
The idea is to throw the quoit at the same angle it's going to land.
You ringed it!
Was that lucky?
It must have been, yeah.
A quoit over the pin is a ringer and scores two points but it's the subtle ways you can block your opponent that makes the game so absorbing.
That's called a...?
Face gaiter.
That is the best shot in the game.
That's what you're aiming to do because nobody can beat that.
If I got this to go like...
No.
Point taken.
Time for my first throw.
Got it onto the clay!
What do you think?
Very good.
I've seen people who would throw ten and not hit the clay.
'It looks easy but it isn't.
The quoit weighs as much as a house brick and is awkward to throw.
'The pin sits in a square yard of dampened clay that helps the quoit to stick.'
Is that what you wanted me to do?
No, but it's a good second.
Throw a Frenchman?
It's the same angle...
But you want to get it on the other side?
Yeah.
Oh!
You knocked me out!
That's the idea.
Hole in one!
We've washed it off now.
What are you doing with the sawdust?
The sawdust is coarse to clean the clay off, but we also dry the quoit as we go.
Tell me about the quoit itself.
It's cut off a log of steel... roughly one-and-a-quarter inch slices.
Then they put it to a lathe, and they're all identical, they all weigh the same.
What is the weight of that?
Five and a quarter pounds.
These are maximum weight.
'Players begin arriving for this evening's game 'and throw a few lengths to set their distances.
'Tonight, I play for Beck Hole against nearby Fylingthorpe.
'It's a friendly, but the two teams are arch rivals.
'The players are paired off and the first to score 21 wins.
'Then it's the overall points total that counts.
The match begins.
'20 years ago, Bill Cockerill was THE Beck Hole player to beat.
He's had to retire through injury but he's still the groundsman and scorer.
I did my shoulder in playing quoits and that finished me.
I've never played properly since.
You still come out and watch and score?
Yes, and get the ground ready.
Still interested.
So you could argue that my being here is helpful cos I'm building up the numbers.
Hope it doesn't do any harm!
I hope I don't do any harm!
Who is your money on to win tonight?
Oh, Beck Hole of course!
Fylingthorpe definitely.
Right, got my quoits.
Time to take to the pitch and meet my opponent.
You must be Mike.
Yeah.
Hi, Mike.
Hiya.
Are you quite new to this?
I've been playing a couple of years.
I've been playing a couple of hours!
Who goes first?
Do we toss for it?
Yeah.
Shall I do the...?
What's your call?
Tail.
That's me.
I go first.
That's good.
He's learned something today.
"He's learned something today!"
Good shot!
Brilliant!
A star is born!
I like this game.
'Mike holds his nerve... '..gets in front... and it's game point.'
How many points?
Two.
Two?!
Well done.
Cheers.
'I lose 21-12.
'But then Colin plays Mike, both former champions.
'In the same 20 match years ago, Mike won but, today, Colin is invincible.'
So there's five points in it?
'Colin launches his final quoit, it's airborne...
'5lb of steel form an impregnable gaiter 'and there's nothing Mike can do.'
120 for us.
125 for Beck Hole.
We won!
'Beck Hole win by 5 points so my 12 did make a difference.'
Ben's had a bit of practice today so I'd like to present this brand-new quoit...to him and if he'd get a bit more practice, he'd make a very good player.
Thank you very much.
My own quoit!
Still to come on Countryfile, why more and more jellyfish are visiting British shores.
Juliet discovers why the world's oldest miniature village is such a big attraction.
As a nation, we all love to be beside the seaside.
But for one of our seaside birds, it seems to be a very different story.
The sight and sound of seagulls - one of the most evocative images of our coastline.
But, during the past few years, they have been forsaking their traditional home for easy pickings in our inland towns and cities, and they've not been making themselves welcome.
Peter Rock is the UK's foremost expert on urban gulls.
He's been ringing and tracking them for 10 years.
Gloucester, which is where we are, has got 2,700 pairs.
They nest on rooftops which, from a gull's point of view - islands surrounded by cliffs so there are no predators, hardly any disturbance, street lighting lets them forage at night.
But, most importantly, in town, the temperature can be 4 to 6 degrees higher than in the surrounding countryside.
That means they can breed slightly earlier, get their chicks off earlier and be in better condition at the end of the season.
Peter reckons there's now about 180,000 pairs of urban gulls.
They've become an expensive pest, as chartered surveyor Nick Jethwa discovered.
We knew there were seagulls already on the site.
The extent of the seagulls was quite a surprise.
The roofing contractors came to do an inspection and found about 100 seagulls nesting on the roof.
We were concerned from a health and safety perspective that people are working on scaffolding and the birds are very territorial so, if they start bombing the roofers, it could cause a real risk.
Some real hygiene problems connected with the seagulls, particularly with their feeding habits.
They were feeding from a sewage treatment plant to the rear of the estate.
In city centres, I've known gulls taking nappies onto the tops of churches where they're nesting and feeding their young with the contents of the nappies.
But Nick has found a 4,000-year-old answer to his gull problem.
There's many different types of birds of prey.
The falcon that we use here is Bella, she's a hybrid falcon.
That means she's a cross between a peregrine and a lanner falcon.
We use that type of bird because the seagulls are naturally very scared of a peregrine falcon.
Take her hood off and she knows that it's time for her to go and play.
She'll fly around.
As soon as Bella goes up into the air, the seagulls will always try and stay above her.
That's because the way a peregrine attacks is to get above their prey and stoop down.
In a stoop, a bird like Bella can reach over 240 miles an hour, which is a lot faster than a seagull.
The gulls are all trying to stay much higher than she is.
She'll be flying around that tree, underneath them, winding them up.
Although as soon as the birds of prey fly, they will leave the area, as soon as they think it's safe, they'll come back.
However, in the long term, it puts them off nesting here.
We don't want her killing things, but the seagulls don't know that.
They will keep well out of her way and they do not want to get underneath her.
She came back when I called her so she gets a big reward.
As far as she's concerned, job done.
The RSPB has supported some control measures.
For example, the use of hawks in some cases can work, but it's not a sustained approach.
Take away the opportunities the birds have to feed and to nest and eventually the problem will go away.
There have been many demands for gulls to be culled.
Could that be the answer?
The RSPB recognises that gulls in towns can be a problem, but we don't think we should resort to culling to control these birds.
Birds like the herring gull has declined by more than half over the last 30 years and we should be looking after them rather than trying to kill them.
The decline of the herring gull is very serious.
It's recently joined the red list because it's declined by more than half.
The herring gull, like some other birds, has a government sponsored action plan.
We should be doing everything we can to safeguard this bird's future.
Their numbers along our coast may be in decline, but the same can't be said for those inland.
Many local authorities want a national strategy to deal with them.
The Scottish Government has pledged to take action against their problem gulls.
You can hear more about those urban seagulls on Radio 4's Costing The Earth on Thursday evening at 9pm.
Seagulls may be deserting our coast, but jellyfish are visiting in ever-increasing numbers as Adam has been finding out.
When I think of jellyfish, I think about being stung by them while swimming in the Mediterranean.
I don't associate them with the cold Irish Sea, but there are lots of these enigmatic creatures in the waters around our coastline.
For the past few years, the Marine Conservation Society have been studying jellyfish types and numbers in the waters around Britain.
They've launched this year's survey to coincide with school holidays.
The man in charge of the scheme is Peter Richardson.
The survey is picking up some interesting jellyfish signals.
Last year, we had an unusually large number of Portuguese Man o' War jellyfish washing up in the southwest.
Last year, at the end of November, there was an unusual invasion of a jellyfish called the Mauve Stinger.
The Mauve Stinger is the jellyfish which is wreaking havoc in the Mediterranean, closing beaches.
At the end of November, a huge bloom of Mauve Stingers washed into UK waters from Northern Ireland to the Shetlands and wiped out some farms in Northern Ireland and on Scotland's west coast, and it was the Marine Conservation survey that picked it up.
You're asking the general public to get involved in the survey.
That's right.
This jellyfish survey has a life of its own now.
Over the past five or six years, hundreds of people have been involved.
Throughout the summer, we often get families going down to the beach and the kids go jellyfish spotting and post the information back to us.
Presumably, you have to be quite careful?
Most of the jellyfish in UK waters are generally quite harmless.
But those that do sting sting quite painfully.
So we always urge people to take part, look but don't touch.
Some of these jellyfish can sting.
I'm now off to meet long-term project member Derek Greenwood who's got a tank to show me jellyfish washed up on Harlech beach.
To avoid being stung, he's wearing gloves.
A couple of compass jellyfish found this morning.
You're involved with the Marine Conservation Society's survey.
Are you finding much on the beaches?
In recent weeks, there's been literally hundreds and hundreds of them washing up.
But unfortunately today we've only found three jellyfish in total!
They must be camera-shy.
What do you do with the results?
I've got a sheet from the MCS which gives you all the different species.
I note them down in a little notebook - how many.
I take them home and then fill in the report form and then post them off to the MCS.
What are the main types you find washed up here?
The main ones are the compass jellyfish, the rhizostoma octopus, moon jellies and lion's mane.
Do you get them coming up onto the beach in quite big numbers?
Oh, yes.
A couple of winters ago, we had some storms and the by-the-wind sailors, they came up on the beach in their millions.
We ended up with a three-mile bank that was two foot deep and four foot wide of them.
Well, if that sent a chill down your spine, how about this?
Swansea University scientists are collecting jellyfish and tagging them.
Now I know all about tagging sheep and cattle, but jellyfish?
It's not as hard as you might think.
The jellyfish we're going to tag are very large animals, up to 30 kilos.
They're the size of dustbins.
And they're not flimsy at all, so we just attach the tag with a loosely fitting cable tie around a certain part of the animal and that's an incredibly secure attachment that won't come off as long as the jellyfish is alive.
How does it work?
Most of what we can see here is just flotation, so that when the tags come off, when the jellyfish dies, they float to the surface and drift ashore.
The electronics is a tiny part of the device in this float.
That'll record two parameters.
It'll record depth and temperature as well.
Those are the two key things that we're going to record for up to a year.
Once you've got that information, how useful is it going to be?
What will it show?
The first vital thing it's gonna tell us is how long the jellyfish live for.
At the moment, we have no idea whether they live for a month, two months or even a year.
With so many jellyfish out there, it seems a little strange we know so little about them.
You're exactly right.
We're now realising that jellyfish may be replacing fish in certain eco systems, so the tide has turned for jellyfish research.
There's now a huge interest in their ecology.
They're also on some people's plates around the world.
They're eaten in the Far East and they're struggling to meet the demand.
That's led to commercial harvesting of jellyfish around the world, for example, in Florida.
Is that likely to catch on here?
It may do.
What we've got to establish is the palatability of the jellyfish we get in UK waters.
If they're palatable to humans, there's no reason why we can't see commercial harvesting in the future.
Not sure if they're for me.
The tagging results won't be out for a while, but if you're on the beach this summer, why don't you report jellyfish sightings to the Marine Conservation Society?
Remember, look, don't touch.
On Countryfile, we get to travel the length and breadth of the British Isles.
Everywhere we go is different with its own scenery and character.
But Juliet has just been to a tiny corner of England where you can experience just about aspect of rural life in a few hours.
It's the world's oldest model village.
Welcome to a land where the wheels of this funfair rarely stop turning, where vegetables are always fresh from the fields and greengrocers have a real vocation to serve their customers and where you can be guaranteed that plumbers' bills won't tip you into an overdraft.
However you can't actually ride on the big wheel, you can't eat the vegetables and the plumbers aren't real because this is Bekonscot Model Village.
It's set for ever in the England of the 1930s.
One and a half acres of land, but in model terms, miles and miles of countryside with a population of 3,000, reflecting every aspect of rural life.
If you thought your builder was slow, it's taken decades to build this house and it's still not finished.
It all began in 1929.
Bekonscot was created by Roland Callingham, a wealthy accountant, who bought some land next to his home in which to set his own model buildings and railway.
Today it's run by a charitable trust.
Would Roland Callingham have approved of what you can see today?
Oh, he'll be rejoicing, wherever he is.
And, of course, he loved this place.
We wanted to keep it unique in the way that if we pitched it where the founder founded it, as it were, it would have a certain...nostalgia.
How do you compete today with other attractions, more modern attractions?
It's really locking it in time, so we know exactly where we are, and we've got white-knuckle rides, but only for the inhabitants in the fairground.
Your miniature fairground.
Down the years Bekonscot has appealed to every generation and received many distinguished visitors.
The Queen came here when she was Princess Elizabeth with her sister, Princess Margaret, and granny, Queen Mary.
I wonder which spot the young royals liked best.
Now, this, to me, looks a little bit like Windsor Castle.
So who knows?
Bekonscot aerodrome makes no concession to modern ways.
Fifty years ago they were proud to show off jet aircraft on the runway, but they've long been replaced by older planes and the visitors seem to like the lack of progress.
I don't find it old-fashioned at all.
It's lovely.
I think it's wonderful.
We've got two young children and they love it.
They've spent a whole day here with their grandparents.
Every time you come here, you see something completely different that you haven't seen before.
It's a feast of intrigue for kids - and for me.
The biggest small attraction here for most people is the railway, 450 metres of track, controlled from its own full-size signal box.
Chris, all of this looks really impressive.
Can you explain a little bit about what we've got here?
What you're looking at is actually a real lever frame from, um...
Purley signal box.
It came to us back in the early '80s.
It is wired into ops and running the railway as a real lever frame would actually control a real railway.
And we can actually play trains!
Can you show me how this works, then?
Yes, sure.
Are we able to play with this without disrupting the entire rail network?
If I want to route something into the station, first, I've got to swing the right set of points.
And then I'll pull the correct lever to signal the train in.
Any signalman could walk in here and use the two pieces of information to control the trains.
It's actually set up as the real thing.
There's one of the trains that we've just signalled in coming down there.
Were trains always your passion?
Certainly when I was younger, I did have a very keen interest.
I used to help my brother when he had a job here and I was nine years old.
But more recently it's about the engineering, the engineering side of things.
So you've been working here since you were nine years old?!
On and off, yeah.
What is it about working here and the model village that you like?
It's pretty unique.
There are only so many places that you could basically turn a hobby into a career.
There's also a miniature railway you can ride on, but I've come to the workshops where new models are made.
The grandstand at Ascot racecourse is the latest.
How long has it taken you, for example, to build this?
So far this has taken two months and it will probably take me another month to finish the whole building.
Right.
Do you do more than one big model a year?
It's probably a project per year, but in between that we'll be fitting in repairing other buildings.
Say, a roof of one of the other buildings might start to rot so we'll have to repair that.
Windows go with the weather, so we're constantly repairing windows.
It's a bit like painting the Forth Bridge.
It's never-ending.
Old buildings can be a liability but don't worry.
The thatched cottage catches fire every few minutes and the fire brigade's always on hand.
But the inhabitants of Bekonscot also need special care.
Mind the sheep!
Mustn't tread on the sheep.
So you made all of these yourself?
Yes.
Fantastic!
How long did it take you to make these farmers?
I started on Monday.
I've still got a few to go, but I'm going to put out these ones that I've made so far.
Do you decide whether they're gonna be happy or sad or cross...?
Yeah.
I decide what they're going to be doing and then I make them happy or unhappy, or serious.
And how long will these figures last out here?
They're braving the elements, these farmers.
They'll last really well until someone kicks them or stands on them.
Um... every year, I take them in and paint them, because they fade with the rain and the sun and everything.
They're pretty high-maintenance characters, aren't they?
Well, it's been great fun stepping back in time, but sadly the moment has come to get back to reality.
Here comes my train now.
Here in Warwickshire, and right across the country, harvest is now well under way.
What's left behind in the fields provides wildlife with some bumper meals.
So lots of different birds and animals are taking full advantage, which is good news for a retired farmer who's always secretly dreamed of being a natural-history filmmaker.
Now at the age of 77, Graham Robson is recording all the wildlife in his rural parish of Marton near Rugby.
So it's a heck of a task that you've set yourself, Graham.
Yes, a tremendous task.
Although the parish isn't very big...
There's an awful lot of wildlife.
There's an awful lot of wildlife in it.
How many species have you managed to capture so far?
I haven't got many of the birds, but I've got most of the butterflies and dragonflies.
If I get 25 of the birds, out of about 90, I'll be doing pretty well.
Some of them never come within range of a camera.
How here's a telltale sign!
That's right, John, because that's barn owl droppings.
Anywhere you see that, it's a sure sign you've got barn owls.
Somewhere around here?
They've been perching on the beam above us.
So you've got a nest in this barn here?
I've got a nest in the barn here that I put up when the barn was built.
Oh, at the far end there.
Ten years ago now.
Four years ago, I put a camera into it.
Two years ago, the barn owls took up residence.
That must have been very exciting.
It was absolutely fabulous because I never dreamt that it would be successful.
I've had a pair of barn owls in it every day almost for the last two years.
They're up there now.
We won't be disturbing them by being so close?
No, they're quite happy to have human company.
They take no notice of us whatsoever as long as we don't touch the box.
It must have been very exciting for you when the first owls went in your box.
It was absolutely amazing.
We didn't really expect success.
Every day, I would check the camera because it transmits a picture back into the house.
And all of a sudden, one morning, we got a barn owl.
The next day we had two.
How many barn owls do you reckon there are now in the parish?
Um, that's difficult to say.
The box here and the box down at the farm, in the last two years, we've successfully fledged 18 youngsters.
The death rate amongst young owls is very high.
They seem OK at the moment?
These are fine, yes.
I checked them this morning.
Graham's created a wildlife reserve on his land where he can concentrate on filming many aspects of the natural world right on his doorstep.
So, what kind of things have you captured on your camera round here?
Well, obviously, because it's got water, I get a wide range of different species.
Quite a few birds.
All the mammals.
Wildlife filmmakers are always looking for a bit of drama...
Yes.
..When they're shooting.
Have you had any of that?
Yes.
Every now and again, you strike gold.
I actually saw a sequence involving a stoat.
It was raiding a coot's nest and the adult coots were trying to drive it away with no success at all.
I was lucky one day to see a kestrel and a squirrel having a confrontation in the kestrel box.
No damage, but there was dented pride, I think.
Graham will soon be releasing a DVD so that other people in his parish can view the wild side of Marton that they wouldn't otherwise see.
Have you learnt a lot, do you think?
I've learnt an awful lot myself.
As I've gone along, I've learnt so many things I didn't know before.
And I've lived here all my life and I didn't know.
Nature's a wonderful thing.
It's a massive influence on everything we do.
We can't actually fight it.
We have to work with it, so let's make use of it.
That's it today, but don't forget, in two weeks' time, we'll have lots of stunning pictures of animals in action when we reveal the results of our photographic competition.
Next Sunday, I'm gonna be in Somerset, where Dunster Castle is getting a green makeover.
Hope you'll have the time to join me.
Until then, goodbye.